Welcome to lecture nine already.
I hope everybody had a good
fall break.
Today we're going to talk about neural
networks
both convolutional neural networks and
transformers
um
and we're going to unpack it to see
what's going on inside.
Um this lecture used to be called
neural network interpretability, but
I've broadened the scope because there
is section now where we talk more about
frontier models
and the interpretability or
visualization methods have not quite
been figured out for most models that
you play with out there. So think about
this one as research areas, what we know
from convolutions, and what we're trying
to figure out for frontier models.
We're going to start with a very packed
agenda with a case study where I'm going
to ask you a question
and let you brainstorm a little bit all
together
on how you would
you know, try to understand what's
happening inside of a frontier model.
Um in the second section we're going to
look at the example of convolutions
specifically and try to interpret
everything possible about the
convolution. Meaning we're going to look
at input-output relationship, we're
going to look at a specific neuron
inside and try to interpret it. We're
going to look also at a specific feature
maps and try to understand what they do.
I will present many methods to do that.
Those methods are real and they've been
used for convolutions um but again,
they're not the methods that you might
see frontier labs use for today's
language or vision
large large models.
However, they're going to bring you the
skills
that will allow you to understand the
methods for frontier models as
researchers are trying to figure them
out.
Um the second half of the lecture is
going to focus more on the modern
representation analysis.
We're going to talk about scaling laws,
capability benchmarking, data
diagnostics, and then I I'll end on on a
few closing remarks.
Okay? Are we ready for this one? Lots of
visualizations in this lecture. So first
um
question for you all.
Um
Let's say the case study is you are a
model trainer
um and you're you know, working on a 200
billion parameters model
at a frontier lab and overnight, you
know, a new checkpoint passes a training
sanity check, but a few issues arise.
Things like
you know, model is getting worse on
reasoning benchmarks
um some safety evals are failing
um and there is a weird spike in let's
say latency for tool use when you
actually use this model for an agentic
workflow.
Your VP is wondering what's happening
and they ask, "What is going on?"
And what are you going to look at first?
So what I want you to discuss
for a minute or so, think about it first
and I'll open up um is what are the type
of evidences that you would look
want to inspect before even, you know,
touching the code or retraining the the
model. What are the things that you want
to look at?
Jump in. There's no single answer, so
I want to know everything you're going
to look at.
Okay, so
um error analysis. So look look at you
said I will look at the reasoning
benchmarks and find the examples where
the model is failing, specifically try
to find patterns in order to pinpoint
what the issue might be. And then same
thing on the safety
um evals where you want to see what type
of safety issues are arising. Is it
everywhere? Is it specific to something?
Yeah, I agree.
Error analysis in general. What else?
Remember, you're you're the model
trainer, so you're training this model.
You're you're supposed to be watching
certain things when you're training.
What can be interesting?
Yeah.
Yeah, let's say not necessarily passing,
but those are great examples. So you're
you're mentioning, yeah, as you're the
model trainer, you would be watching the
training loss. And you want to see what
what what are you going to look for in
that training loss?
Okay, convergence.
You probably want to make sure that it's
smooth.
You don't want big spikes.
Um how about the validation loss? What
is your expectation on the validation
loss?
Yeah, it should probably follow the same
curve as the training loss, but is
likely higher cuz you're probably
performing slightly less well on the
validation set than on the training set.
If you're seeing spikes, it might
it might lead to certain it might mean
there's some issues.
Um what else
are you looking at?
Yeah.
So this batch you mean? Yeah, yeah,
yeah. So you're looking at this round of
training data. Maybe the last round of
data that we trained on
there was some issue in that data. Maybe
that data was
you know,
probably you know, poisoned or biased
toward a certain category of data that
we're failing on. You're you're totally
right, yeah.
Maybe that specific checkpoint is doing
poorly compared to the previous
checkpoint and so you have pinpoint you
pinpoint where the issue arise, you
know, during the the training. What else
are you looking at?
Yeah.
Okay, because it's overnight and it
seemed everything was good up to
yesterday and now there's an issue,
maybe you're saying there is a hardware
issue. Yeah, we could check actually is
Yeah, latency has been
uh pointed out, so maybe the the
hardware has failed. Yeah, you're right.
What else?
So we we we a lot of the answers are
global answers. You're looking at the
model in general. You're not looking at
specific portions of the model. What
would you look at if you were to inspect
the model more precisely from the
inside?
And this one's a language model, so you
can you can think about the fact that
it's a language model.
Yeah.
Mhm.
Yeah, you're right. Like you want to
look at different checkpoints
and see where did we fail and might be
able to trace back to that moment and
figure out what the issue was. So for
example, maybe your initialization
was actually pretty good and the first
checkpoints were doing well, but
suddenly at some point
the model saturated in a certain way.
Maybe you're seeing exploding gradients
or vanishing gradients in certain
moments and you want to pinpoint that.
What what else?
We're we're adding so many methods right
now, but I want to hear
what else you have for language models.
What other things can you visualize for
language models that might
might mean something's going wrong.
Yeah.
The attention maps.
Yeah, yeah, fair enough. You've learned
about transformers in the online videos.
The attention maps which are
representative of you know, the
relationship between different tokens,
they might not make sense to you. You
might actually be plotting certain
attention maps and be like
this token has nothing to do with that
one, but the model seems to think it
has. And you might be able to
identify certain issues with the
attention maps.
What else beyond the attention maps?
What what yeah.
So you mean tell me more about the
sensitivity analysis. What would you fix
for example and what would you change?
Yeah.
Okay. Yeah, but I like the idea of
sensitivity analysis. You might fix you
might I try to figure out which hyper
parameter went wrong.
Is there something wrong with our
optimizer? Is our learning rate schedule
poorly tuned? Um
Uh maybe scaling laws, you know, we know
that we can play with compute, we can
play with data, we can play with model
size and one of those might be going
wrong.
Maybe an analysis would allow us to
identify uh the model is fine, it just
needs to be trained longer or uh the
model is actually too small for the
amount of data we're giving it, you
know. That type of stuff would come with
um either doing a sensitivity analysis
or uh comparing what we're doing to the
scaling laws that we know from other
models.
Uh we're going to look into that.
Okay, any other ideas?
Might be. So you're you're saying you're
you I gave you 200 billion parameters,
which is a very large model even as of
today. Uh it might be over
parameterized. That's a good question
because it depends on what it's been
trained on, how much data we're feeding
it, how much compute. It's all relative
to each other, but yeah, it's a large
model, so I would expect a lot of
compute and a lot of data along with it.
Um you know, in fact, a lot of these
models might be built as a mixture of
experts. You you've you you've heard
about mixture of experts. One thing that
could happen is that some of the experts
are failing.
And you might be inspecting if experts
are in fact failing or the routing
module is um always selecting the same
expert because it's just you know, found
an expert that is really good and
generalized and the other experts are
not being used. That might be another
issue. as well. Uh that might, you know,
be related to the model capacity because
if the model is not using all its
experts, it's probably not actually
operating as a 200 billion parameter
model. It's operating as a smaller
model.
Yeah.
Okay. So, you know, generally this is to
motivate the lecture. We're going to
look into all of these together today.
All right. And we'll start with
convolutions uh because they're very
visual. For the convolutional part,
we're going to go super deep um
but then for the frontier models, I'm
just going to get broader and and give
you the areas of research. So, the
answer to the question I asked typically
would fall under four buckets, every
solution that we looked into together.
One is training and scaling. So, people
are looking at loss curves, at, you
know, um things like gradients, uh
learning rates, mixture of experts,
routing, scaling laws. We're we're going
to talk about all these. Um the second
category is representation and internal
aspect of the model. You mentioned
attention, um heads and maps,
embeddings. Nobody mentioned embeddings,
but you could actually visualize
embeddings and see does it make sense to
you? Are these um, you know, tokens
close to each other as you would expect,
meaning the the model's mental
understanding of language is correct. Um
And then neuron level behaviors,
although that's really hard with a large
model.
Um and nobody has quite figured it out
yet.
Um and then
the other category might be data and
distribution. Maybe
you know, the actual
uh benchmark that we're looking at has
been contaminated. Meaning, you know,
the model
is just not either is doing too well on
that benchmark or it doesn't mean
anything or is doing poorly for a
certain reason because
the data distribution used in the test
set is completely different from the
training or validation set.
Um and then, you know, it might be
failing at different levels. You can run
benchmarks on the language model. You
can run benchmarks on the agentic
workflow that is using that language
model.
And because you want the language model
to be used in agentic workflow, those
are two levels that you need to inspect.
So, for example, when uh a frontier lab
says um our model is doing really well
for tool use, what they mean is the
language model has been tested on
upstream tasks in a workflow and it's
actually good at tool use
against their benchmarks. So, those are
different levels
of capability analysis.
Okay. So, let's talk about uh
convolutions. We're going to dive deep
inside convolutions and then we'll go
back up and look at frontier models.
Okay?
So, um first case study uh for
convolutions.
Let's say that you have built an animal
classifier for a zoo and they are very
reluctant to use your model um without
any human supervising because they don't
understand the decision-making process
of the model.
How can you alleviate their concerns?
How can you give them intuition about
the decision-making process of the model
so that they feel like, ah, the model's
doing mhm things that feel natural and
and human.
So, let's say just to simplify, let's
say you have a
a convolutional neural network and
there's a softmax layer and it's
supposed to identify animals. So, the
number of classes are many animals.
Yeah.
If you were to write a quick Python code
to give them some intuition, how would
you do it?
Yeah.
Okay.
Good. Good. Good. So, just to recap, um
the zoo is not AI native, so you have to
explain certain things. You're going to
tell them what softmax is. So, we're
going to have a probability for each
animal classes. That's how it works. Um
and on top of that, you also mentioned
you might talk about convolutions and
say here are how features are
identified, here's how a filter scans
through the image and, you know, we're
expecting these to learn. So, you're
going to educate them first. That's
totally right. The second thing you
mentioned is maybe you run a a data set
search. So, you can try to build their
intuition by showing them animal
pictures and showing that the model's
doing well. And yeah, I agree. Those are
good approaches. We're going to see how
to do a proper data set search large
scale. Uh but what else can you do uh
that's going to give a little bit more
confidence cuz this is explanation, but
it's not proof that the model is looking
at the right place systematically. Yeah.
So, you say you you ideally you would
give them intuition at the at the filter
level. Like this filter, we know it's
responsible for finding the legs of an
animal. That's what you're saying. So,
how would you do that?
You know, good you know, intuition.
You're asking is it as simple as just
printing out the weights of that are
identified or the feature map that
results of that filter? Um unfortunately
not usually because that might be true
for the first layer,
but as you get deeper, things mix up so
much that you know,
if you were just to print the uh filter,
it wouldn't make um any sense. Pretty
much.
Um but there are other methods that
we're going to see. So, your intuition
is right. We're we're going to try to
give them that. Something simpler.
Input-output relationship. How would you
show that um
that the output
is actually related to the right
portions of the input for this dog, for
example?
Yeah.
Yeah, confusion matrix across a lot of
data. You would find true positives,
false, etc. Yeah, correct. Something
else?
So, similar to what he said with um you
want to give them intuition from the
inner workings of the network and you're
saying how about we mask the latter
parts of the network and we treat every
intermediary layer as an output and
analyze if the output makes sense. Yeah,
we're going to look at that actually. Um
yeah, those are more advanced. What I
was looking for is even more more basic,
much more basic. It's uh if you want to
show the
uh relationship between an input and an
output of a CNN
or you know, any vision model,
you might take the score of the dog in
the output layer, okay? And what is
exactly this quantity? What what what is
the intuition your intuition for what
this quantity means?
Take the derivative of the score of an
animal class with respect to X.
With X being the input image.
Yeah.
Yeah, how does the score of dog change
when you move pixels around?
Which is what you want, right? You want
to be able to If you can do that, you
would indicate that which are the pixels
of the image that if we change them, it
changes the score of dog.
If you can print that, then you would be
able to show this is where the model is
looking at when it's predicting a dog.
Right?
So, yeah, if you actually calculate this
derivative,
you would get something like that where
some of the pixels are going to be
brighter, meaning their gradients is
higher, and some of the pixels are going
to be darker, meaning we move that pixel
and it didn't modify the score of dog at
all.
That's a very quick way to look at which
pixels in the input were relevant for
the score of dog.
Uh now,
why should we select the score of dog
pre-softmax versus post-softmax?
It's usually a very common mis-
misconception.
Yeah.
So, what's the issue with the scaled
version?
Class of dog. Yeah, so
what what you said is the the
post-softmax
score is not only depending on dog, it's
also dependent on all the other scores.
So, you could actually
take a pixel, move it, and it happens to
modify the score of a panda because
there's a panda in the background or
something, and it would influence what
you're trying to show, but you're only
looking at dog. You just want the score
of dog to be influenced. So, that's why
in this method called saliency maps, we
use the pre- softmax scores that is only
representative of the class at hand that
you're analyzing.
Okay? So, you could do that, and
actually, if you were to in the past,
not anymore, but you could use that for
a quick segmentation sanity check
because the pixels that are brighter,
the gradients that are brighter are
representatives of the pixels that
should be overlaid on the dog.
And in fact, if you do the saliency maps
and you realize that the pixels that are
bright when you compute that gradient
are all over the place, it's probably
that the model is not even looking at
the right place. It's just getting
lucky.
Okay?
So, this first method, saliency maps,
now have that in your toolkit. Very easy
to implement, right? You just write a
Python script, you you perform the
gradients calculation, you print it.
It's a matrix of
pixels that are brighter or darker, and
you're done.
One of the main
issues with saliency maps is that it's
looking at just a pixel level,
which doesn't make too much sense if you
want to interpret semantically where the
model is looking at.
You know, the model will never see a cat
or a dog with one pixel being different
than the rest. It would be too
discontinuous. So, instead, there's
another method. I'm not going to go into
the detail, but I linked the paper,
which is way more common, called
integrated gradients.
And integrated gradients, the idea is
that instead of doing that directly by
taking the DS of dog over DX, we're
going to take an image of the animal,
and we're going to generate, you know, a
sort of many pictures that are
taking dark, completely black zeros
a pixel all the way to the animal,
the final image, and then we're going to
look at the path of gradients across all
of this update, and it's going to be way
more interpretive. I'm not going to go
into the details, but integrated
gradients is just an extension of
saliency maps that happens to use a
different formula with an integration
and is way more common. Um if you look
at it practically, this is an example
from the medical field. Here is an image
of a retina, and
if you perform the integrated gradients,
you would see that
the original
image the the
the annotation for the lesions are
exactly where the model is looking at
when it's giving you a probability that
there is a lesion.
Okay?
So, second method called integrated
gradients.
Let's push it a little further.
The next case study is
that, you know, you you you
you you want to now tell them a little
more about the decision process
of the model
with
um
I guess
I guess let me let me rephrase.
The saliency maps looked at the pixel
level.
What what you can do in order to give a
better intuition, which was mentioned
earlier, is another approach called
occlusion sensitivity, which is actually
way more
intuitive and simple, where you could
actually, you know, take the dog image
and paste it into the CNN, and you would
get a score of a dog. You could also
overlay a dark square. So, zero out or
mask partially the input image and give
it to the same CNN and track the
modifications on the score of dog that
you're tracking.
If you actually do that, you can plot a
probability map of how is the score of
dog changing as I move the dark square
through the image.
So, let's do it together. I'm going to
say that, you know, this one when you
when you actually put the dark square on
the top left of the image, the score of
dog is unchanged. It's still very high.
Now, you move the square a little bit to
the right, and you see that it's still
very high, the score of dog. You do it
again, still very high. Now, the square
is partially occluding the face of the
dog, and you should see the score of dog
drop if the model is in fact looking at
the dog. And you perform that many
times, so you scan through the image
with your dark square, and you plot what
we call
you know, the
the probability map of the true class
for different positions of the gray
square.
Does that make sense?
So, pretty simple, computationally
expensive, though.
Just have to rerun the image so many
times through the model.
Here, practical examples
to look at. The first one,
the true label is a
Pomeranian, cute dog, and you see that
the model is
failing to recognize the true class when
the square is overlapping with sort of
the center of the face, which makes
sense because here the true class that
we're tracking is not dog, it's
Pomeranian, and I could see how if you
occlude the face, it's hard to get the
breed of the dog.
The second example, the true label is a
car wheel. Sorry, I hadn't shown you
that. The true label is a car wheel, and
you can see that when the square is on
the wheel,
it is
it is in fact dropping in terms of the
true class probability.
And then finally, the Afghan hound.
What's interesting about that third
example is the probability is dropping
when the square is on the dog, but it's
also increasing
when the square is on the face of the
human on the left, which means that if
you actually occlude the the face of the
human, the model thinks even more that
the true class is in fact an Afghan
hound.
You're just removing additional
unnecessary information for it to
discover the true class. So, this model
seems to be doing well, right? It seems
to be looking in the right place.
We call that occlusion sensitivity,
pretty simple, another tool with
saliency map and integrated gradients in
your toolkit.
Let's push it slightly
further.
Um
Here, we're given,
you know, along with the classification
outputs, we the zoo wants a real-time
visualization of the model's decision
process, and you have one day to show
that, and we're talking about
convolutions again. What do you do? So,
the important part is to know
the methods that we've seen so far are
sort of post methods where you analyze
the output or you show something. Here,
we're looking at a
sort of ideally a a module that we could
plug in our network that would
constantly give us the decision-making
process of the network, or at least
where it's looking at.
How would you do this?
This is our network, by the way. We're
taking an input,
we're adding zero padding, and we have a
series of conv relu max pool blocks.
And then at the end, we flatten. We have
a triple fully connected layer, a
softmax, and we get our probability
output for classification.
So, just first question, where do you
think is the weakness of this network
when it comes to interpreting where the
model is looking at on a picture?
A part of this architecture is very
makes interpreting the network way
harder, yeah.
Why?
Yeah, totally right. The fully connected
layers, you're looking at all the pixels
at the same time. You're mixing
everything and you're doing it three
times. So, by the end of those three
layers, the information has been mixed
together, essentially. You do not find
the localized information that you have
pre that with the max pools and the conv
layers. So, how could you change that
layer in order to avoid that? How would
you modify your network if you wanted to
retain maybe the the the performance of
the model, but not lose that localized
information?
Yeah, good idea. How how could we
instead of doing three, can we do one?
Can we you know, still have a layer that
makes the
you know, makes the interpretation easy?
Actually, there's another trick which
we're going to see, but it's similar to
what you
described. Let's say we convert this
network into something where the you
know, the flattening of the pixels and
the fully connected layers are converted
into a single global average pooling
layer and a fully connected layer.
So, here we reduced from three to one,
the fully connected layers. We still
need our fully connected layers in our
soft max because it's a classification
task and we want a good decision engine
at the end.
But, we converted we we added a global
average pooling. So, let me explain why
why this is better.
So,
the last conv block, essentially, is
giving us a volume. For the sake of
simplicity, let's say that volume is a 4
by 4
with six channels.
Okay?
And I color coded them for simplicity.
So, each of these channels is a feature
map that is resulting from a filter
being scanned through
the previous input, right?
Everybody is clear on that?
So, global average pooling
is going to take each of these channels,
feature maps,
and is going to average them in a single
number.
So, if you take the orange
matrix
and you average it, it gives you 104.7.
You do the same thing with the green
one, the blue one, all six of them and
you get a volume or call it a vector of
size six.
116.
So, why is that interesting? Because we
actually did not lose the localized
information.
We did not mix things up. We just
assigned a single number
to a feature map that we retained. So,
the localized information is still there
on the previous volume.
And now we can treat that as a vector
that goes through a decision engine or a
fully connected layer that ultimately
goes through our soft max and give us
the probabilities.
So, this architecture
is easier to trace back to localized
information in the input space because
you can actually look at let's say one
of the score of dog and you can look at
the weights
of each of these edges that tell you how
much has the feature map from the volume
before contributed to that score.
So, in other words, if I had to
summarize, let's say the feature map
looks like this. So, this feature map is
very high has somehow activated heavily
in some portion of the input image.
The others, similarly, have activated to
other things. You're taking the weights
from your fully connected layer. By the
way, you have to retrain that layer. You
have to just train that layer, that last
one.
And then you sum all of them and it
gives you what we call a class
activation map for the class that you're
visualizing.
So, you're overlaying those last six
feature maps and you're weighing them
with the weights of the last fully
connected layer. You're not losing
information. You're not mixing three
fully connected layers that are
impossible to trace back to the input
space.
Okay? So, if you now give it an input
image and you overlay the class
activation map for the score of dog,
which you can do for other classes. You
can do the same thing for the class of
cat, look at the different weights, the
feature maps, and maybe for the class of
cat the the weights will will certainly
be different. So, the contribution of
each feature map will be different.
Yeah, and this is what you get. This is
called class activation map. Um
and
it's from folks over at Berkeley. And
so, here's a video that describes it. Um
it runs really quickly. You can think of
it as a slight modification to a
vision network that can allow you to
unpack what's happening inside and
what's the decision process.
There is also um
sort of an improvement to the CAM or
class activation map algorithm called
Grad-CAM, which enhances that method.
Okay?
Any questions on class activation maps?
So, we're getting to know convolutions a
little better, yeah.
Yeah, so you were saying in the video,
it seems like the model sometimes is
looking at meaningless things. Yeah, I
mean, it's not surprising, frankly. This
is the previous generation of models.
Um and on top of that, you're looking on
a video.
The model is a classification network.
So, it might look sometimes at things
that are not even labeled.
And so, it has to find the closest one.
It might not make sense at all. That's
why you build that type of module to
visualize and understand like
the network's actually not working that
well. Yeah.
Yeah, but maybe on the main objects that
you actually want for your task, let's
say the zoo wants to do very well with
cats and dogs. You can verify that when
a cat is moving even at fast speed, the
model's quickly looking at it, you know.
Super. Let's do a couple more methods
because it's going to build our
intuition um
for frontier models.
Um so, now the zoo trusts you. It trusts
that the model correctly locates
animals, but they get sort of scared and
they wonder if the model understand what
a dog is.
Like does it understand actually what a
dog is or is it just like pattern
matching random things?
Um
you know, how could you
um take this conv net
and sort of query
what the dog what the model thinks a dog
is?
How would you do that?
How could you ask the model, what's your
best representation of a dog?
Okay, yeah. You did say two things. So,
get an image,
so a forged image that maximizes the
probability of dog. Yeah, let's do that
actually. And then on your second point
um
about
reverse engineering, we're going to look
at the method there as well. But, yeah,
I agree. You could So, how would you
concretely do that? Like what would you
maximize?
Okay.
Actually, what we said earlier, but I I
I think you came right after that the is
we would not take the soft max output
because the soft max output is dependent
on other classes. You divide by the sum
of the exponentials of other classes.
And so, you could actually maximize the
soft max output by not maximizing the
class you want, but by minimizing the
other classes, which is different than
what you want.
So, um here's what we'll do. We'll
define the loss function where we take
the pre-soft max score of dog, so the
thing right before the soft max, which
is only dependent on that specific
class. And we might also regularize it
to make sure it looks natural. The
reason we want the regularization term
is because pixels need to be between 0
and 255,
roughly. And so, you don't want to run
an optimization
a problem where pixels can have values
that go all over the place. It's just
not going to look good to the human eye.
Um
and so, we're going to do that. We're
going to run a gradient ascent
algorithm, so similar to what we've seen
in some of the previous classes, um
where we are going to update the pixels
of an input image, a completely random
input image, until we can maximize the
loss function we defined. Um so, we
forward propagated the random image, we
compute the objective, we back propagate
all the way back to the pixels and then
we update the pixels to maximize that
objective and we do that many times
until
we end up with something that might look
like this.
So let's say we take the score of a
Dalmatian
you know here
researchers
and
showed and this is work for J from Jason
Yosinski
shows that you can start seeing the
model if you ask the model what is a
Dalmatian and it will tell you it's
something with black dots on a white
background.
roughly
So actually might not understand fully
what the dog is but it that's what it
thinks it is.
So we just unpacked it a little bit and
queried queried that.
Another interesting one is if you look
at um
the goose. So here the the the top left
label
goose
for the model is many of them.
What does that mean? It means probably
the model has seen a bunch of
geese all the time together and has
rarely seen a single one.
And maybe the labeled data was labeling
that as goose when it was geese and so
the model actually doesn't understand
that it's a single one. It thinks that
all of them
are the label.
That makes sense?
Okay.
Super. So that's called class model
visualization. You can actually Oh
sorry, I wasn't showing what I was
talking about. No, I was right. The
the
the way to improve those visualization
is just to change some of the
regularization methods. So the
researchers have shown that you can
actually
add more color by regularizing better so
it looks better to the human eye and
then it becomes easier to query the
model for a variety of classes just to
make sure that it understood those
classes.
And so same with flamingos
actually the label flamingo to the model
feels like many flamingos.
Just something you can observe.
Any questions on class model
visualization? Nothing's super new just
another
um
you know tool in your kit.
It turns out you can apply the same type
of method as class model visualization
but instead of doing it at the class
level
you it in
an intermediary activation. So you could
actually do the same exercise sort of
what you were saying earlier with the
masking of the later layer and just
looking inside the network. You could
pick an activation in the network create
an objective function with a
regularization and say
hey show me the input picture that
maximizes this activation.
And that should tell you
what is
the input that maximizes this activation
the most.
Right?
Okay. So that's class model
visualization which can also be applied
with gradient ascent anywhere inside the
network at any neuron.
And that already gives you a some sort
of a
a method to look at the neuron level and
say hey what's the input that maximizes
the fake input that theoretically you
could generate that maximizes that
activation.
Um
the next method is actually the most
commonly used today because it's so
simple and intuitive. It's a data set
search.
So
what you could actually do is to pick a
filter
you you just pick one filter you pick
its feature map
among you know
I guess you pick one feature map at some
point in the network such as
after this max pooling layer and
so let's say you have 256 filters in
that convolution layer so you have 256
feature maps of size 5 by 5
and you
find across all your data your
validation set the top five image that
maximize this feature map.
Yeah.
So you just track the activations in
that feature map you find the highest
activation across all your data and you
find the top the top five images and you
can do that you know again you would say
this seems that the filter um
that produced that feature map has
learned to detect shirts because if you
find the top five images that activated
that feature map the most that filter
the most
it's all images of shirts.
If you were to find something like this
you would say it seems that the filter
has learned to detect edges.
And you could do that across every
feature map
to interpret your filters.
Okay, simple data set search
that can allow you to interpret if a
if a filter is reacting to something
meaningful.
So if you look at these pictures that I
printed at the bottom of the slide
they're all cropped.
So why are they cropped?
They don't look like images from the
data set. The the image is probably
bigger than that, right?
Hm?
The the what?
So so we took we so we took the input
image we send it through the conv relu
blocks.
And then we pick a feature map in the
fifth block let's say.
What is this feature map looking at? Is
it looking at the whole image or no?
Sorry, what is the
So we pick a feature map and in that
feature map we find the activation
that's the highest. So let's say the
activation is the
row number five column number three.
If you pick that activation
does it have access to the entire input
image or not?
Hm?
Yes, so you don't necessarily have
access to the entire image. The best way
to visualize it is at the first layer.
You see on the first layer you take the
input image you take a filter
and you run it through well that
activation in the feature map of the
first layer is only going to see what
the filter sees, right?
When you go deeper in the network do you
see more or less on average of the
image?
A single activation does it have access
to more or less parts of the image?
Say more?
Yeah, it's more.
Let's look at it. So here's a picture 64
by 64 by 3 let's say.
We have a conv network five layers
and after five layers
the last conv has 13 filters
and leads to a 13 by 13 sorry it has 256
filters that leads to a 13 by 13 feature
maps.
Um
if I look at this feature map let's say
that's the most activated um
I trace back to the input space
it will have access to
this part of the image let's say.
Now if the there was another conv relu
block
and I was looking at a feature map it
would have even more abstraction of
multiple portions of the square so it
would actually see slightly more from
the input image. Does that make sense?
So you know that that's that's that's
how you would think about it. And it
makes sense because at the end of it the
last output has access to the entire
image, right? Because all these
things are are adding up um
to the prediction.
Okay. So the deeper the activation the
more it sees from the image and that's
why the images were cropped. They were
just cropped based on tracing back what
that activation was looking at in the
input image which you can do very simply
um computationally.
Okay. So now we're going to look at our
last method for convs which has to do
with reverse engineering a conv and then
we'll move to the frontier models.
Um
So
remember this slide from when we
introduced generative adversarial
networks GANs?
Um I didn't talk too much about the
generator architecture. I just said it
was a neural network but I did mention
that something's weird about that
network which is that the input is way
smaller than its output. The input is a
vector Z the output is an image
of more dimensions.
Um it is very common that such a network
needs to upsample and thus would use a
deconvolution.
Sometimes in the literature you're going
to see dimensions of deconvolutions as
an upsampling
network with the input is
smaller than the output.
>> [snorts]
>> Um sometimes those are called transposed
convolutions, but we're going to talk
about why.
Another example where you might run into
upsampling is when you have an
encoder-decoder type network such as for
segmentation. So, let's say you're given
an image of a cellular a a set of cells
like this,
and then you want to label segments that
belong to a cell just to find the
different cells. Uh typically you would
use a a set of convolutions that reduces
the volume in height and width.
And then
you'll get information encoded in a
dense format that you will then upsample
because your output should be of the
size of the input minus the number of
channels, but at least every pixel
should have its own class.
And so, typically that would be a set of
convolutions
followed by deconvolution. So, you
downsample, you upsample.
Um
why am I talking about deconvolution?
Because we're going to try to reverse
engineer uh
conv networks by adding
a module a deconvolutional module that
will take a specific activation and will
reverse engineer the trace to verify
what was the reason this activation was
high.
Okay. This idea is key not only for
convs, but for any network you'll think
about
in the future when you work on it if you
want to actually reverse engineer uh a
the reason a specific neuron has been
active.
So,
let's take the example of a 1D
convolution. This is the most uh
uh basic example just for the the sake
of understanding the math.
Um
and I give you an input X
which has um
some padding with two zeros at the top,
two zeros at the bottom, and then X1
through X8 values, and I send that input
to a 1D convolution which has one single
filter of size four with a stride of
two.
What's the size of my output Y?
Remember the formula.
What? Five. Five, correct.
Yes, I assume you you did this.
Um this.
So,
you know, you took the
an X you
applied the formula and you you floored
it, you didn't forget to add one.
Um and then you ended up with five. Is
that it?
Yeah.
Correct.
Super.
So, we have our output of five, and
let's say we define our filter size four
W1 W2 W3 W4. Um it's actually easy to
see that the conv 1D can be written as a
system of equations
where Y1 equals W1 * 0 + W2 * 0 because
of the padding plus W3 * X1 + W2 * X uh
W4 * X2.
Right?
You're just overlaying
the filter on top of the first four
indices of the inputs
and you're doing a dot product.
Same thing with the second one, third
one, all the way to the fifth one, and
that's your system of equation that
describes this conv 1D.
Now,
because it's a system of equation, you
could actually write it as a matrix
multiplication. So, you could say
the conv 1D is literally just a weight
matrix that we multiply by the input.
So, the inputs and the output sizes we
know, 5 1 and 12 1.
So, the weight matrix is necessarily a 5
by 12 weight matrix.
So, we just
rewrote the conv 1D as a single weight
matrix that you multiply by the input,
get the output.
If you were to, you know, draw this
matrix, um this is what it would look
like. So, it would be a matrix with
values all along the diagonal, and the
rests are zeros.
So, that's our conclusion. Conv 1D can
be rewritten as a matrix vector
multiplication.
Everybody follows?
So, if you can write it as a matrix
multiplication, remember we're talking
about reverse engineering, then I could
say
um
deconv
is possible. It's possible to reverse
engineer that. And in fact, I'm going to
make a very
uh big assumption that is not always
true. Sometimes it's true, but for
practical reasons we're in deep
learning, right? It's an engineering
field. Um we're going to assume that W
is invertible
um and so, you can find a matrix H that
is equal to the inverse of W
um
such that X equals HY.
So, that you're able to reverse engineer
uh the signal.
Uh I'm going to make a second assumption
um and the sizes I printed, which is
even bigger, is that W is not only
invertible, it is also orthogonal,
meaning that its inverse is
um
its transpose.
It happens that it's sometimes true, and
in fact, if you think about an edge
detector, so let's say our filter is -1
0 0 1 uh 0 0 0 1. It's it's a it's a
edge detector. Sorry, I have one too
many zeros, but it's an edge detector um
and it's actually um
you know, invertible, and its inverse is
its transpose.
Um and so, that simplifies our reverse
engineering
because we have a conv 1D
and we know that we can write it as a
matrix vector multiplication, and we can
transpose that matrix to reverse it.
And maybe it's not always true, but it's
true enough for it to work in deep
learning.
Pretty much.
You're going to do that so many times,
right?
Um
that's why in the literature often time
deconvolutions are called transposed
convolutions.
I give you the 1D example. The 2D
example is similar, it's just more
complicated. There's more math.
Things mix up, but you know, same same
idea.
Um now,
there is a trick that makes it simpler
to
code the deconvolution.
Um
and to see that trick um
I just drew um X equals W transpose Y.
So, you have your X which is a vector of
size 12, although there's two padding at
the top or at the bottom. Um and then I
transpose the W matrix that I was
showing you um
and then I multiply that by my vector Y
of size five. Um it's
act this is actually a transposed
convolution with stride two is
equivalent to something slightly
different, which is a subpixel
convolution of stride 1/2.
It's a mathematical trick.
You can do it at home, but you would see
that uh these two operations are
equivalent, meaning you can actually um
flip the filter. So, you see in the
right side uh in the left side of the
screen, the filters are flipped. So, if
you look at the first row of my matrix,
it's not W1 through W4, it's W4 through
W1.
So, I flipped the filter
and I scanned it all the way through the
diagonal.
I also used another trick, which is my Y
vector
I inserted zeros in between the values.
It's called subpixel.
So, I inserted zeros, and I also added
some padding.
So, a couple of tricks, but
no no need to to remember it by heart.
If if there's anything you can remember,
it's that implementing the deconvolution
in the subpixel version I was describing
is is similar to a convolution, but what
you do is you create a subpixel version
of the input by adding zeros in between
the values and padding it, you flip the
filters,
and you divide the stride by two.
And that's what a deconvolution is. So,
if you have a convolution on your
on your network, and you want to reverse
engineer it,
you take the filters,
you flip them,
you create a subpixel version of the
input,
you divide the stride by two, and you
run the process, you will have reversed
that convolution.
The reason we're doing that is because
we're just rewriting the convolution as
another convolution, but the
hyperparameters are different, but it's
easy to code.
Right?
You're just reusing the same code,
pretty much.
So,
anyway, let's get back to our example
here. We have
um
an image of a dog.
We run it through a conv net
um and we pick at some point in that
conv net
a feature map.
We pick one feature map only among the
256 possible feature maps right here.
And we're going to look at the max
activation of that feature map. So, we
find the max, let's say it's this one.
So, row two, column three is the maximum
number of that feature map.
We What does it mean? It means the
filter that led to that feature map,
when it looked at its input, it was
maximal in that location. It's maximally
activated in that location.
We zero out every other
um
entries of this
matrix.
And then we reverse the network. So, we
max pooled, we unpool. We relu'd, we do
the reverse. We do a deconv instead of
the conv, which is a transpose
convolution, subpixel version, flip flip
the filter, divide the stride by two.
And we do that how many times? Three
times because we have three blocks.
And then
we should be able to reconstruct
what this activation was maximally
activated for.
And we get the cropped version, as we
learned, the cropped part of the image
that this activation was looking at, and
exactly the pixels that maximize its
value.
Does that make sense?
It's pretty complex,
but it's important to know these methods
because you might run into something
similar in the future
or be asked to sort of interpret certain
feature maps, certain activation maps,
etc.
Um
Okay.
So, some additional details that we'll
cover is what is unpool and why do we do
some relu in there. So, very simply,
um
let's say I take the max pooling layer,
I max pool this.
Filter size
two by two, stride of two.
Um
if you wanted to unpool this,
how would you do it?
Are pooling layers, max pooling layers,
um invertible?
Mhm?
No. Why?
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly. It's not invertible
because if you pick you write the the
six here on the top left,
you can tell that the six was in one of
these four, but you don't know where it
was.
You can't invert. And it's very
important to know where it was, right?
Um
So, it's not invertible, but you could
actually use a trick to make it
invertible, um which is
passing what we call switches.
So, during the forward propagation, you
look at all your pooling, your max
pooling, and you remember with a binary
matrix, a very lightweight matrix, where
the pooling happened, where the max
pooling happened. And then when you're
doing the unpooling, you remember those
switches, so you keep them in memory,
and you pass them back, and that should
tell you
where the value came from.
Yeah.
So, that's what we mean by unpooling.
Okay? So, I go back to my previous map.
The only thing I need to change to be
able to reverse engineer my network is
to pass the switches
and the filters, by the way, because the
deconv is just the flipped version of
the filter
with subpixel and stride divided by two.
And so, I do that.
So, you can see you can you can
literally invert your network here and
trace back from one activation to the
input space.
Um and then for relu is a little odd.
I'm not going to spend too much time on
it because it's more empirical than
nothing. But relu forward is essentially
zeroing out every value that is negative
during the forward path. Technically, a
relu backward is impossible unless you
have also the switches.
If you have the switches,
um you could actually um you know,
pass linearly back whatever was kept
because it's the identity function.
Uh but but actually that would kill your
your um
positive signal coming back. So, instead
you just reuse relu.
Uh
basically, you you reuse a relu because
you want to start from the activation
that is the highest on your feature map
and to keep passing the positive signal
back to the input space. Don't worry too
much about
It's just that relu is just passed as a
relu during the reconstruction process,
not as a proper relu backward.
Okay? So, here we go. We send our dog
through the network.
Uh we look at a specific
uh max pool output. We take the feature
map. We find the activation that is the
highest in that feature map. We zero out
all the rest. We reverse engineer our
network. We find the cropped part of
this dog with the pixels that led to
that specific feature map shining. We
are interpreting the filter that led
that feature map. And you can do that
anywhere across
um
across the network. But of course, if
you're earlier, the crop is going to be
even smaller.
If you're later, generally bigger.
Okay?
So, you learned deconvs
transpose convs.
Now, let's look at some practical uh
visualizations from uh Matthew Zeiler
and Rob Fergus. Uh these these are great
researchers in the space of
visualizations, been making so much
progress.
Um
So, they trained the network.
Okay? They looked at results on a
validation set of 50,000 images.
And
um
so, what you're seeing is the first
layer and specifically the patches. What
the patches are, they're the top nine uh
strongest activation per filter.
Okay?
So, for each filter in the first layer,
they look at the top nine strongest
activation, and they re- remember the
data points that was leading to that.
So, that's the data set search method
that we saw together. What are the nine
images that led to that maximum um
that that that feature map activating
the most. Print them. Those are the
patches for each filter. If you do that,
you can already um
interpret some of the filters
um by seeing that, oh, this one reacts
to edges that are diagonal, or this one
reacts to edges that are straight,
for example.
On the bottom right, uh we actually
print the filters raw. And of course,
because it's the first layer, it is
interpretable. So, if in fact you have
an edge detector, you should see when
you print that matrix that it looks like
an edge detector.
That doesn't work for
layers beyond one.
So, now let's go a little deeper. Now,
we're going layer two,
and we're looking at the deconvs. So,
what are they doing? Um
they're essentially um
they're essentially looking at the top
one strongest activation per feature
in the second layer. So, the second
layer has 256 feature maps
represented here.
You pick one feature map.
You look across all these
50,000 validation images. You find the
maximum
feature map. You take the specific
portion of that feature map, the
specific entry that's maximally
activated. You zero out the rest. You do
your deconv. You pass the switches, blah
blah blah. And you get the cropped part
of the image that represents why it was
activated. And this is printed all over
here. And you can see you can start
interpreting that by doing the top one,
or you can do the top nine. And if you
actually do the top nine, um you would
start seeing that in fact uh certain
filter have very clear purposes. Some
filters detect circles. Some filters
detect
odd uh
you know, shapes.
Yeah?
If you keep, you know, doing that in
layer three, you would start seeing with
the deconv method that the filters are
capturing more complex information.
Remember in the first lecture we did
together, I said that the deeper you go
in the network, the more the information
uh um
adds up, and you get more complex
features later. This is a proof of that.
Pretty much.
Now, if you go to layer three, and you
pro- you you you can do you can do all
of it. You can do the top nine patches,
where if the nine patches look very
similar, you you know, you can probably
safely say that this uh filter was
responsible for this type of uh shape or
color or um
um you know, uh salient feature.
And uh and then you can do the deconv as
well, um essentially.
Let's watch together a very short video
of Jason Yosinski
that shows a little bit of everything
we've learned together. They can
recognize school buses and zebras and
can tell the difference between Maltese
terriers and Yorkshire terriers.
We now know what it takes to train these
neural networks well, but we don't know
so much about how they're actually
computing their final answers.
We developed this interactive deep
visualization toolbox to shine light
into these black boxes showing what
happens inside of neural nets.
In the top left corner, we show the
input to the network, which can be a
still image or video from a webcam.
These black squares in the middle show
the activations on a single layer of the
network. In this case, the popular deep
neural network called AlexNet running in
Caffe.
By interacting with the network, we can
see what some of the neurons are doing.
For example, on this first layer, the
unit in the center responds strongly to
light dark edges.
Its neighbor one neuron over responds to
edges in the opposite direction, dark to
light.
Using optimization, we can synthetically
produce images that light up each neuron
on this layer to see what each neuron is
looking for.
We can scroll through every layer
class activation within convolution,
pooling, and normalization layers.
We can switch back and forth between
showing the actual activations and
showing images synthesized to produce
high activation.
This is a class model visualization
method.
By the time we get to the fifth
convolutional layer, the features being
computed represent abstract concepts.
For example, this neuron seems to
respond to faces. We can further
investigate this neuron by showing a few
different types of information.
First, we can artificially create
optimized images using new
regularization techniques that are
described in our paper. That's the class
model
visualization.
We can also plot the images from the
training set
>> That's the data set search. as well as
pixels from those images most
responsible for the high activations.
And that's the [clears throat] deconv.
This feature responds to multiple faces
in different locations.
And by looking at the deconv,
we can see that it would respond more
strongly if we had even darker eyes and
rosier lips. We can also confirm that it
cares about the head and shoulders but
ignores the arms and torso.
We can even see that it fires to some
extent for cat faces.
Using backprop or deconv, we can see
that this unit depends most strongly on
a couple units in the previous layer
conv4 and on about a dozen or so in
conv3.
So, because of deconv, you can trace
back the entire layers before and where
Okay, I'm I'm going to leave it to you,
but you get the idea. The
these researchers built a toolkit that
essentially reproduces some of the
methods we've seen together, although
we've seen more methods than what's in
the toolkit.
And so, your your your kit is now able
to answer many questions about
convolution such as, hey, what part of
the input is responsible for the
outputs? We now know that we can use
occlusion sensitivity or class
activation maps. Um what is the role of
a neuron filter layer? We have many
methods that can allow us to do that.
Can we check what the network focuses on
given the input image? We have methods
to do that. And how does a neural
network see our world? We have the
gradient ascent class model
visualization method that allow us to
maximize
an input image with respect Sorry, find
the input image that maximizes a certain
activation.
Super. So, that was the first part
and then we're going to move toward
frontier ideas.
Um
Any questions on
CNNs? Do you feel like you have a better
idea of how to look inside a CNN?
So, let me start by
comparing
CNNs
to more
you know, modern frontier networks. Um
The core distinction is going to be that
CNNs uh
deal with localized information. They
visualize edges, textures, and shapes
when in modern call it LLMs,
um we visualize relationships and
meanings
between concepts or between tokens.
And this is because transformers are
based on
attention.
And that started with the attention is
all you need paper, uh which essentially
explained why attention on its own is
highly performing and can allow us to
model very complex relationships.
So, um you know, by the way, this is
just the the the the first figure of the
attention is all you need paper, which
you should all be able to read and
understand by now in the class. Um
And transformers really represent
language um using two very simple ideas
that are uh visualizable. They They're
We can interpret them to a certain
extent.
The first one is the attention um
patterns.
Um you know, attention
looks at the relationship between
tokens. So, you look at a specific
token, which can be a word, a subword,
or a syllable. You know, I'm going to
simplify by saying it's a word and its
relationship with other words in the
training set.
And that's the attention um that the
transformer's looking at it. Um
Each attention head learns a different
patterns, so it can learn things like
linking pronouns to nouns or tracking
structures or enforcing a certain
ordering.
And then um I really like this uh
visualization,
which is from um
Jesse Vig in 2019.
Um and this visualization essentially um
shows you There's a very nice blog post
that he wrote um with a few figures
where you can see um he he presents how
um attention can be visualized in simple
ways. What is the connection between a
fixed token with the surrounding tokens?
That's it.
Um
So,
this is essentially the transformer
analog to the CNN saliency maps
that we looked at.
Pretty much.
Uh the other uh things that transformers
or more modern language models uses
embeddings.
You know, during the pre-training phase,
you're also learning embeddings. Um
You are ready to read the BERT paper in
fact now with the baggage you have from
the class.
Um
and um what's interesting about the
embeddings, and I printed a picture here
from um Garden 2021.
I also encourage you to see that uh
short blog post where he uses a
visualization method called t-SNE. It's
a dimension reduction method. We're not
going to present it in the class, but
it's taught actually a lot in the in in
biotech and healthcare. It's used very
extensively uh for those of you who work
with the Stanford Hospital.
Um
And it allows you to visualize
embeddings. And embeddings are sort of
how the language model perceives our
words, so you would expect tokens that
should have similar semantic meanings to
be next to each other in that space or
tokens that have nothing to do with each
other to be far away from each other in
distance. And that can be a way to
sanity check that your model actually is
learning meaningful um representations.
All right. So, together, attention and
embeddings
are what let large language models track
relationship and meanings. And um and
you can uh visualize your embeddings
with dimension reduction tool. You can
even
visualize attention relationships as
well. Um unfortunately,
the modern transformers are so
complicated that even the cutting edge
research is only able to interpret those
relationships
with two-layer transformers, pretty
much.
The best you find out there is probably
Anthropic's work, so I linked two
papers. The first one is called the
mathematical framework for transformer
circuits, which is essentially um
explaining how the different components
within a transformer interact with each
other. Uh and they introduce the concept
of a circuit. And then the second one is
a follow-up to that paper called
in-context learning with induction
heads. Induction heads are probably the
best tool we have to sort of visualize
what's happening inside a transformer.
It's pretty complex. You should be able
to understand it by now, uh but you'd
have to spend um quite some time to go
deeper into it. I just will link them.
We're not going to talk about it for the
sake of time.
Uh
let's get to
some fun stuff. Training and scaling
diagnostics. So, how do labs frontier
labs check if a model is training well?
We've talked about it in the first case
study, but one uh very natural way is to
look at our loss curves. You can look at
the training loss, at the validation
loss, and make sure that they follow
sort of a smooth trajectory. And if it's
not smooth, there's probably something
that went wrong. You've probably trained
your own network where some loss
functions look very funky. I remember
back in the days there was even blogs
where people would post their ugliest
loss functions and there was a lot on
there.
Um
You might find sudden jumps on the loss.
That means uh maybe the the batch that
has been processed has been corrupted.
Uh maybe you're doing extremely well on
it when you should actually not
you know, do that well and it might
raise a flag. Um
you might, you know, find bugs in your
code because of that. you might find
gradients that are exploding, gradients
that are vanishing.
Um all of that you could visualize at
the loss function level.
Now, note that loss functions can be run
at a global level or at a you know, on a
specific subset of your data. We're
going to talk about it in data
diagnostics.
Um the other things that are interesting
to track also sometimes referred to in
the in the in the community as a
training telemetry is um to watch and
track your gradient norms. Um
uh look at your learning rate schedule.
Um
or even look at hardware efficiency
metrics to feel if you've underutilized
compute, which we talked about again in
the first part. So, imagine that if
you're working at a major frontier lab,
you probably have a a dashboard that
tracks your different loss function for
different subsets of the data, your
checkpoints, all of that, you know. Uh
you would have all of that.
Unfortunately, very few of these are
published because they're IP, you know.
They can't really They don't want to
give it out uh because it will um leak
essential information about their
architecture, about what's going well,
what's not going well, etc. And that's
why you find very few um information on
these.
The one thing that I I I I you do find
some charts on that are really helpful
is scaling laws. So,
scaling laws, which we've talked about
in a previous lecture, um
is essentially trying to understand the
relationship between our model
performance and some um other um call it
hyper parameters, such as the model
capacity, so the size of the model, the
amount of compute that being used, or
the data set size.
Uh DeepMind has done amazing work. Um I
think it was in 2022, a couple of years
ago, uh which in Chinchilla. Um
this chart is
you know, borrowed from the Chinchilla
paper, where essentially what I want you
to look at here is uh they're comparing
the Chinchilla model, the green star, to
other models, including GPT-3, which
came up, you know, a little before. And
what they're showing is that um
the scaling law is actually slightly
different than what OpenAI thought.
And they analyzed GPT-3 and they said
GPT-3 is actually not performing well
enough for the size that it is at. And
it was found that GPT-3 was not trained
for long enough. They essentially
explained that if you kept training
GPT-3 for longer, um you would have had
way better performance. And it was not
about the model size. In fact, the model
was underutilized.
So, they plotted these lines. So, the
dotted line is what probably we thought
in 2020-21
the scaling law, the power law would be.
And they showed that it's actually not
exactly that.
Where um
essentially the idea is they plot the
the the the the full line here and they
say, "This is our analysis of the
scaling law. If your star is above that
line,
it's probably that your model should be
trained longer."
Okay? If it's on the line, it's
respecting the scaling laws that they're
finding.
And that's what's interesting about this
Chinchilla paper. Yeah. So, this is
after OpenAI
So, that's after the GPT-3 paper.
Chinchilla came in 2022 saying, "You
should have trained GPT-3 longer. You
would have done better." And here's
Chinchilla uh model that has uh less
parameters than GPT-3, so 70 billion
versus 175 billion, um and that is
performing better.
Yes.
To go deeper, I also pulled a few charts
uh from um that that that show you the
power laws between um you know, the the
loss function. So, on the vertical axis,
you have the test loss.
Okay? That shows
essentially your performance on the test
set. And then on the horizontal axis, on
the x-axis, you have compute, data set
size, and parameters. So, how are those
scaling laws established? Essentially,
they fix two of them and they vary the
third one and they see if things are
respected. Meaning,
let's say you're um increasing the
you're keeping the same compute, the
same uh
uh
data set size, but you're uh training a
model that is twice as big
in log uh uh in in logarithms, um what
what does it tell you about the
performance? Essentially, are those
scaling laws respected? And so, what's
nice now is that we have a precedent for
scaling laws. So, if you were actually
training um
such big models, you would uh compare to
the scaling laws that are available out
there.
Remember, another reason these are
important is because models training
runs are so expensive.
It wasn't shared publicly, but we we
estimate that uh GPT-5 is probably in
the hundreds of millions.
You know? And so, you want to know,
"Should I train that model twice longer
or not?" Because that's a big financial
decision, right? And the scaling laws
allow you to determine, "Should I invest
in compute? Should I invest in uh uh
growing my data set, so finding more
data? Or should I invest in model
capacity, making my model bigger?"
Okay?
So, yeah. Together, these form sort of a
health dashboard for the model.
So, that's training and scaling
diagnostic, loss functions, you know,
etc. Um health dashboard, scaling laws,
all of that are things that researchers
might use to get a broad sense of where
to invest more in terms of uh improving
their model.
The other one is something we've already
seen to a certain extent is how models
how labs evaluate model capabilities and
safety. Um and they might do it with
benchmarks. So, capability benchmark
might be evaluating the model in, you
know, tasks like reasoning or coding or
math or multilingual tasks, etc. It
might also be comparing checkpoints that
help you understand how your model is
improving over time, depending on what
you're feeding it, or depending on some
um hyper parameters that you're
tweaking.
Um
and also
error clusters. So, just to tell you a
little more about error clusters, um if
you actually use benchmarks across a
wide variety of tasks, you might see
that oh, the model checkpoint number
five is actually doing very poorly at
reasoning. Let's see why is that.
So, here are some examples um
from a competitive math benchmark, um
2025 aim, um
published by OpenAI on GPT-5. And
actually, the bottom one is from today.
This morning, Mistral announced their um
their
third generation model. So, I thought
I'd pull it to show you that how real
time these things are. It just published
today.
You know? And they're comparing across
reasoning and math and etc. Um against
benchmarks. Now, the risk is uh
are these benchmarks contaminated?
You know, how how can a benchmark be
contaminated?
Yeah.
Yeah, if it was in the training data.
The problem is these models are trained
on so much data online. You don't know.
Maybe it was trained on a blog post
where someone actually was presenting a
benchmark and describing what the
benchmark was about. Maybe it was
trained on GitHub and there was a text
file in a very shady part of the GitHub
that was listing some of the test sets
uh information. All of those might
contaminate benchmarks. How would you um
identify that a benchmark has been
contaminated?
Test set has been contaminated.
Yeah, Llama 4 you brought up, just to
repeat. Um
looked good on benchmark, looked poorly
poor on pract- in practice after the
community tested it. The general
consensus, I mean, my opinion is
I I actually don't look too much at the
benchmarks when a foundation model
provider publishes them. Or in other
words, I would look at them in relative
value between models rather than
absolute value.
And you'll wait for the community to
test it on agentic workflows, on their
tasks, and then people will sort of get
a taste for if it works or not and on
what it works.
So, it took some time, for example, for
the community to realize how good Claude
was at coding. It's like it wasn't clear
from it was clear from the benchmark,
but others were also clearly good. But,
you know, over time people felt like,
"Oh, wow, it's actually really good at
coding." You know?
Yeah. You had a question or no?
Okay.
Um cool. So, oh yeah, contamination. So,
you know, we um how how to detect if a
test set has been uh
you know, exposed?
Few few methods.
Um
some
you know, researchers might do a
a search within the data set. So, let's
say you have a training set and you have
a held out test set, and you actually
look for n-grams. So, you take uh
sequences of tokens of size seven,
eight, and you search through the train
set and you find that uh their same
n-grams is also found in the test set.
There's a chance some of it has been
contaminated. You can do it uh
also uh with hashes or with embeddings.
Actually, maybe the test set has been
contaminated, but not word for word.
Maybe semantically, and so you might do
the same thing with an embedding and run
a search and say that oh wow, this
specific example from the test set um is
found in the training set semantically,
very similar stuff.
So, you might actually run analysis to
figure out if it's contaminated. And if
you find that your test set has been
exposed or you have a reason to think
it's been exposed, what do you do? You
would usually uh fix the test set. The
test set is smaller, you would remove
all those examples that you think are um
exposed and you would replace them with
brand new ones that are completely held
offline in a folder that is separate,
not available online, etc.
Yeah.
Uh then there's a problem of safety
evaluations. I'm not going to spend too
much time on it, but safety um
is uh important to foundation model
providers. Uh they stress test their
model and there are many adversarial
attacks, jailbreaking, social
engineering, misuses. Um they also
assess harmful um content generation,
hallucination, privacy leakage, etc.
etc. Um
and then they also look at how the
foundation model behaves in an agentic
workflow, as I was saying earlier.
So, not only evaluating it um
sort of one-shot, but evaluating it in a
workflow.
Here are some examples of uh
actually very nice joint collaboration
between OpenAI and Anthropic
uh from last year, where they worked
together to assess the safety of their
models and they tried to jailbreak the
model, to social engineer, and they
published some um
um
findings on password protection or
phrase protection. I linked it and I
would encourage you to quickly look at
it. They wrote prompts to try to extract
a password from a model um and see if
the model was good at not um
you know, leaking the password.
Example.
So, these dashboards um essentially
inform the go, no-go decision for
uh you know, releasing or for
determining what the RLHF will be based
on. So, if you're actually going to do
supervised fine-tuning or uh re-
reinforcement learning from human
feedback, you it's expensive and you
want to do it on the stuff that's
failing.
So, if you identify exactly which evals
are failing, you will then use that
information to focus the RLHF on that
specific problem and save a lot of money
and human time.
Uh
lastly, let me see if there is anything
else I wanted to mention here.
Um
yeah.
Yeah.
Uh let's talk about the data diagnostic
and we'll end on that.
So, uh
data diagnostics. This is probably the
last area that uh frontier models are
very focused on. So, how labs detect
data issues.
Um
there are
many things you can do, but I I really
like distribution checks. So, I I pulled
this chart from uh
paper called Pile, The Pile from 2020,
uh where the pile is a very large data
set, 800 GB, that is made from diverse
texts. Um and they kept the data domain.
So, they explain using that figure what
the data set is made of. So, the data
set might be made of um information from
free law or it might be made of
Wikipedia, Stack Exchange, GitHub with
coding. And so, you have different
domains within that data set. And in
fact, when you train a model on that,
you can plot the loss function across
the entire data set or you can plot the
loss function across different domains
within that data set, which give you
more intuition for um where it might be
failing or working. And so, you might
want to track domain proportions in your
data set. And domain proportions also
matter because it is observed that if um
certain uh domains are underrepresented
in the data,
the performance of the model on that
domain is likely going to drop in
comparison to another domain.
So, all things are not equal, you know,
you if you actually have so much, you
know, we we remember with the speech
recognition example where I said you
have too many zeros and too few ones and
so the model just doesn't learn the
ones.
Um
yeah.
This is also a problem with online
learning. So, imagine, you know, those
frontier models, they're learning live,
right? Like often time they're just
being fed data constantly and maybe the
batch from the last month had very
little coding data. And so, the last
portion of the training, the
distribution of the coding domain um or
the frequency was lower than other
domains. And so, sometimes you might see
a drop in performance for a specific
domain if you're not careful.
That can be fixed with sampling, like
smart sampling. You remember what we saw
in reinforcement learning with the
experience replay, where we actually
kept experiences and we put them in a
replay memory and then we sampled from
that. Those are the types of method,
sampling methods, that allow a model
provider to make sure they keep the
frequency of data domain the same at
different portions of the training.
Yeah.
Uh yeah, token statistics, just to
mention it a little bit. Um you know,
you uh you want to count the frequency
changes for key uh tokens, which I was
mentioning. So, let's say
you know, a a math token is
underrepresented,
um that will be a problem. That, you
know, the derivative symbol is
underrepresented, that might actually
lead to way worse performance for that
specific task where you ask the model to
make derivatives.
Um
and so, labs often time monitor uh token
drift or distribution or the frequency
per token and they use sampling to fix
it. And finally, the contamination
checks, which we have um talked about
earlier. I also give you concrete
examples, not going to go through all of
them, but you know, these are examples
of token distribution drift reports, uh
tokenizer statistics that um
issues that that that I I raise here um
or some anomalies on um
uh you know, corrupt data
detection. So, if I if I read one of the
examples for you,
um
let's say um
let's pick this one, maybe.
Um you know, non-English tokens increase
from 12% to 19% after a new web crawl,
where that might mean that the domain of
that specific language is increasing
relative to others and that might lead
to a an increase in performance or a
drop in performance for a different
language.
As simple as that.
Okay.
To summarize everything, uh
what are examples of things that
frontier labs monitor?
Global training loss, validation loss,
both global and domain-specific on the
subset of the data. Uh scaling curve
alignment, you know, comparing your loss
test loss to your compute, to your data
set or to your model capacity.
Um
or we didn't talk too much about router,
but mixture of experts, you know,
imagine you have a
a lot of the models that are top models
right now are mixtures of experts,
meaning that in your transformer uh
block um for the multi-layer perceptron,
there's actually multiple experts that
are being trained in parallel and there
is a router that will route that batch
of data to the right experts, to top
one, top two, top three experts. And
it's very common for the router to fail,
to or to always exploit the same mixture
of experts. You need a mechanism to
detect when this happens. And so, you
might have in your health dashboard some
sort of a router information or whether
the mixture of experts are all used as
much as each other. Sometimes certain
experts are going to be so specialized
that they're never going to be used,
almost. And you want to avoid that. And
you might do some load balancing to
avoid that.
Um you know, gradient norms,
learning rates,
um checkpoint-to-checkpoint eval
benchmark, token distribution, tokenizer
statistic. We we we covered all of that
at a high level. And as I said earlier,
uh frontier labs rarely publish uh those
dashboards because it's IP and because
it can uh leak certain deep information
about their IP and how their models are
trained. Um and so, you usually learn
about these things year after year. You
might You might learn about these things
on a model that last that that came out
3 years ago or 4 years ago and they're
okay now with sharing it.
Um it's pretty common.
Okay.
Um
so, closing remarks. Any questions
first? Or yeah.
Um so, do you So, for example, like for
is
training coding models, right? So, do
they care more about like tokens that
are
showing
like in coding general, or are they like
are they more worried about like having
that diverse tokens?
Yeah, so you're asking if Anthropic is
training Claude code, do they care
mostly about coding data, or do they
also add other data? Yeah.
Yeah, it's a it's a tough question. I
don't have the exact answer. It's been
shown that certain domains might improve
the performance of other domains. So, I
imagine that in coding,
you know, if you have math data, maybe
math data actually helps the performance
of coding, especially for functional
programming. Let's say coding languages
that are more mathematical.
Um but, I could clearly see that if they
were training Claude code on web crawl
and everything, it would not perform
well because you would have so much crap
data that is not relevant for what
you're trying to get the model to do.
And so, I think there's a balance
between those things.
So, it's safe to say like you would want
to be like that.
Like any you would want to include
neighboring domains as well.
I think you could run experiments. So,
would you include neighboring domains?
If I were training um
Claude code um and I had a lot of money
to do that, I would probably uh you know
maybe you would you start with a Python
language and you get as much and there's
so much data on Python language. So, you
probably have enough already there. But
then, you want the model that scales to
other programming languages. Well,
probably Python is useful for C++. C++
is useful for Java. And then, functional
programming, if you're going to Elixir
um you know, Scala, things like that,
they're helping each other probably to a
certain extent. Uh but, you will need to
have a representation of those. I I
could see that
I'm I'm I'm pretty sure, and I don't
work at Anthropic, so I don't know, but
I'm pretty sure, let's say a language
like Rust increases in popularity, which
is the case, right? Um and then, in the
data distribution, you start seeing more
frequency of those tokens from Rust,
does that
affect the performance on other
languages? Probably yes, that's my
guess. And how do you track it? This is
all of what we talked about. Like
Yeah.
Yeah, question is um
you know, let's say we we trained on
everything online and now uh real data
and now what about synthetic data?
Should we use it a lot? Should we use it
uh
strategically? What's the future of
that? Um
so,
uh depends of
are you talking about general purpose
models or not, specialized models. In
general, uh
it is a good idea to do data
augmentation, to use synthetic data.
Although, I would always watch the um
the token frequency, meaning you know,
you can't cuz synthetic data is way
cheaper. And so, if you actually
generate so much synthetic data of a
certain data domain, and then it impedes
on the rest and lowers the performance
on the rest because the model just is
always trained on that synthetic data,
then that's a problem. In practice, I
think also the returns of synthetic data
might be plateauing at some point. Um
the recent news, I guess, and if you
look at uh
um at the DeepMind paper, um it's
probably that we're lacking high-quality
data more than we're lacking synthetic
data for most domains right now. Uh but,
who knows if it's going to be the case.
You know, some other people would say
what we're actually lacking is letting
these uh agents play in RL environments
in the wild and generate their own
synthetic data
uh or real data, but part of a game. Um
you know, nobody has quite the answer. I
would just say the trend has gone from
Actually, you should look at the a paper
from Epoch AI. Maybe you you you've seen
that already, but Epoch AI has a really
nice research report, which says
by I forgot the exact numbers, but it's
in there. By 2020
um uh 2025, the world would have exhaust
the the frontier labs would have
exhausted low-quality data available
online. By 2000 in text.
By 2027, low-quality data in audio,
image, and video would have been
exhausted. By 2030, high-quality data
would also have been exhausted. And at
that point, it's like, what's next? You
know, um
probably by that time, data is not going
to be the bottleneck anymore, uh and
it's going to be more about model
architecture.
Potentially.
Are we producing more data than we're
using? Uh probably yes, but it doesn't
mean the models are not plateauing.
The data that, you know, you go and you
code in Python,
your Python code is going to be already
online somewhere, most likely, or 99% of
it. So, the model is actually not
learning that much from it.
It's just more data, not higher-quality
data, and that's why I think the plateau
is there. Like, maybe the best
radiologist in the world is producing a
research paper that is so unique that
it's high-quality
by definition of what the models feel is
high-quality today. But, you know, how
much of that can we expect?
Yeah, it's risky. Like, is it risky for
the model to like the model, let's say,
is online learning, so it's learning
from new data being produced by
everyone.
Um is that going to
uh risk the model performance to drop?
Um essentially, that's what you're
asking, or
Yeah, yeah. In that case, yeah.
Yeah, the data produced is also coming
out of AI. Yeah, for sure. More today
than before. Like, coding data today
is increasingly used by
um you know, by by uh is it increasingly
generated, and so it's just fed back.
So, just long story short, it's not that
interesting
for training.
Super.
So, closing remarks uh and reminder on
what's next. Um so, by the way, I hope
you feel after this lecture that you
have a better understanding of the
techniques that you can use in order to
look inside the model, look outside the
model, both for CNNs and for frontier
models. Um again, it's just a
2-hour lecture. We don't have time to go
so deep as much as I would like it in
each of these domains. Um
I uh it's my last lecture at this
quarter.
Um and so, thank you for participating.
I um enjoyed spending time with you all.
Um I hope uh you spend time on your
projects. Projects can be very
delightful in CS230. Over the years,
I've seen people use their projects to
get a job, to start a company, to make
friends. And so, I don't think you will
regret putting time and effort into your
projects, even if we don't have too much
time left. Um those are the the last um
you know, milestones for the or or
deliverables for the class. I hope you
enjoyed the class. We're always looking
for uh feedback. And so, um I'm eager to
hear from you all. Thank you.